Today we are dealing with the Seven-Circle-Theorem.
The Seven-Circle-Theorem states the following:
Let C_0 be a circle and C_1, ..., C_6 circles contained in C_0,
such that each inner circle is tangent to the outer circle
and any two adjacent inner circles are also tangent to each other.
Then the three diagonals of the hexagon formed by the intersections of the inner circles with the outer circle meet
in one point.
Our goal now is to prove this theorem.
We will be able to do this by embedding the problem in a Hyperbolic framework.
First, we give a small introduction to Hyperbolic geometry
in order to reformulate and further work on the problem with our newly gained knowledge.
Axiomatically, the Hyperbolic space differs from the Euclidean space
in that the parallel axiom does not hold.
The parallel axiom states
that for every straight line g and every point P that does not lie on g,
there is exactly one straight line h that runs through P and is parallel to g.
Parallel here simply means that the two straight lines do not intersect.
This property does not exist in Hyperbolic geometry.
There, for every such g and P there are several - even infinitely many - straight lines through P
which are parallel to g, i.e., do not intersect g.
However, our representation here is misleading,
because of course g will be intersected by all but the original line h
if we follow them long enough.
In general, we have the problem that we want to
represent a Hyperbolic space in the Euclidean plane - this video.
So the question we are now addressing is:
How do you represent the Hyperbolic plane in the Euclidean space?
There are different models for the Hyperbolic plane.
Such models are simply mappings from the Hyperbolic to the Euclidean plane.
We take a closer look at the Poincaré and Klein models.
First, let's take a closer look at the Poincaré model.
The representation of the hyperbolic plane in the
Poincaré model is limited to the unit disk.
The geodesics of the Poincaré model are - in contrast to straight lines in Euclidean -
circle segments that intersect the unit circle at right angles.
This makes it clear that the parallel axiom does not apply here.
For a point P and a geodesic one finds any number of other geodesics that
intersect P but not the original geodesic.
Even if it seems so at first glance,
the hyperbolic plane is by no means limited.
If we let a point in the hyperbolic plane
move in one direction with constant speed,
we see that it never reaches the boundary of the Poincaré model.
The unit circle is at infinity and does not belong to the Poincaré model.
The following representation of the distortion is helpful for further understanding.
This is a tiling of the hyperbolic plane.
All these triangles have the same Hyperbolic shape and area.
The Poincaré model thus provides a highly distorted representation of Hyperbolic space.
Now we consider the Klein model.
We will see strong similarities to the Poincaré model.
The biggest difference is that geodesics here actually correspond to Euclidean lines.
However, since these are limited by the unit circle, as in the Poincaré model,
the parallel axiom does not apply here either.
There is also a strong distortion of space in the Klein model.
Here, we see the same tiling of the Hyperbolic plane in the Klein model.
Towards the border, distances also become larger and larger here.
Since both models represent the same space,
it is obvious that there are mappings that identify the points of the models with each other.
In fact, they exist. We call them f and f^ -1.
As we see here, the formulas for these mappings are fairly simple.
With f and f^-1 we can now transfer objects from one model to the
other, especially geodesics.
Since the mappings act pointwise, intersections between geodesics are preserved.
This now gives us the following reformulation of the Seven-Circles-Theorem.
Let C_0 be a circle and C_1 to C_6 ​​circles contained in C_0 such
that each inner circle is tangent to the outer circle
and any two adjacent inner circles are also tangent to each other.
Then the three hyperbolic diagonals of the hyperbolic hexagon
formed by the intersections of the inner circles with the outer circle meet
in one point.
When we have proved this theorem,
we simply apply the transformation from the Poincaré to the Klein model
and have thus also proved the original theorem.
Now we introduce some new concepts in the Hyperbolic space.
Let's take a closer look at the behavior of circles and
radii in hyperbolic space.
To do this, we compare it to the Euclidean circles we are familiar with.
A circle consists of all points that
are the same distance from their center P.
In Euclidean, of course, we measure distance with the Euclidean distance function.
Hyperbolic discs, which we embed in the Poincaré model,
are defined exactly like Euclidean circles,
except here we use a different distance function to measure lengths.
At the center of the Poincaré disk, the hyperbolic circles look the
same as the Euclidean ones.
If we now change the center,
the shape of the hyperbolic circles still corresponds to that of the Euclidean circles,
but the center of the Euclidean circles no longer
corresponds to that of the hyperbolic ones.
Let's take a closer look at the hyperbolic radius.
This is measured using the hyperbolic distance function,
which measures the distance between two points b and c
in the hyperbolic plane.
For the calculation we still need the intersection points
of the geodesic with the edge of the unit disc.
We call these points a and d.
To evaluate the hyperbolic distance function, we
interpret points a through d as points in the complex number plane.
Although it doesn't seem like it to us,
the hyperbolic circle is at every point the same distance from its center.
If we move the hyperbolic center to the edge
and look at the associated concentric circles,
the hyperbolic radius converges to infinity
and we get so-called horodisks.
Having got a feel for circles in hyperbolic space,
we now look at hyperbolic hexagons in
order to then be able to define the alternating perimeter,
which is of great importance to our main theorem.
A hyperbolic polygon is defined as in Euclidean,
but the curves connecting the vertices are
not straight lines, but segments of a circle, as is always the case in the Poincaré model.
The corners of the polygon can be anywhere in the hyperbolic plane.
If the vertices all lie on the edge of the Poincaré disk,
we call our polygon ideal.
As in Euclidean,
the perimeter of a hyperbolic polygon can be defined as the sum of the side lengths.
Note that we are measuring the hyperbolic distance of the vertices.
In the case of hexagons, an even number of corners can
also be used to define an alternating perimeter.
Instead of taking the sum of all side lengths, we now calculate the alternating sum,
i.e., subtract every other length.
So now let's look at the alternating perimeter of an ideal hexagon.
The problem here is that the individual segments S_k
have infinite length because they touch the border.
So we cannot calculate the alternating perimeter directly.
However, geodesic segments that do not touch the boundary have finite length.
We can take advantage of this in the following.
We trace the alternating perimeter of an ideal hexagon
to that of a non-ideal hexagon.
Since its edges have finite length, we can explicitly calculate the alternating perimeter here.
To do this, consider a sequence P_n of hyperbolic non-ideal hexagons
that converge to an ideal hexagon P_∞.
We now put a disk D_i at each vertex of P_n
so that consecutive disks do not overlap.
Further we define S_k^~ as the edge to the borders of the disks.
We see that the lengths of the S_k^~ are finite.
If we change the radius of a disc,
we add and subtract the same amount on both sides,
in this case for S_1 and S_6.
So the alternating perimeter is independent of the size of our disks,
even if our disks have zero radius.
It follows that the alternating sum of S_k is equal to the alternating sum of S_k^~.
If we let n go towards infinity,
this relationship still applies.
But since the lengths S_k^~ are now finite,
we have actually found a meaningful calculation for the alternating circumference.
Now let's consider an ideal hexagon.
If we connect the opposite sides of this hexagon,
we see that a triangle is formed in the middle.
Let's call this triangle T_P.
We now show the following theorem:
For any ideal hexagon,
the alternating perimeter is exactly
twice the perimeter of T_P, except for the sign.
For the proof we first define the notion of a semi-ideal triangle.
It has two corners on the edge of the circle - that is, ideal points -
plus one corner in the hyperbolic plane.
In our ideal hexagon there are three such triangles: Y_1, Y_2 and Y_3.
There are also
three more semi-ideal triangles on the respective opposite sides,
which intersect the inner triangle T_P.
We call them G_1, G_2 and G_3.
We define a quantity similar to the alternating perimeter for hyperbolic triangles.
If we remove disjoint horodisks from the two ideal nodes of the triangle,
we get lengths L_1', L_2' and L_3'.
We use this to define the alternating perimeter of a semi-ideal triangle
by adding the two blue lengths
and subtracting the red one.
The alternating perimeter does not depend on the size of each circle,
since the same length is both added to and subtracted from it.
The triangles G_k and Y_k each share exactly one node for k=1, ..., 3.
In each case there is an isometry I_k that
maps the opposite triangles to each other.
We can construct this as follows:
With the help of so-called Möbius transformations - isometries in the hyperbolic plane -
we can map the intersection of the two triangles to the origin.
The two diagonals that intersect the point are now both straight lines through the origin.
Therefore, we can simply do a point reflection at the origin,
transforming the right triangle onto the left.
Of course, the whole thing works not only for the first pair of triangles,
but for all of them.
Since we have an isometry between the two triangles,
the alternating perimeters of the triangles are the same.
We can write these formulas explicitly for all three pairs of triangles
and bring the perimeter of G_k to the other side.
Now we can add everything together and get the following formula.
What does this sum actually mean now?
Let's look at the whole picture.
If we subtract the perimeter of the G_i,
a part with the perimeter of the Y_i cancels out.
We see that we have summed twice
the perimeter of the inner triangle as well as the alternating perimeter of the hexagon.
Overall, our assertion follows.
Now we are finally ready to prove the Seven-Circles-Theorem.
Let's look here for a Hyperbolic hexagon with circles
tangent to the large circle,
with adjacent circles touching at exactly one point.
If we now look at the alternating perimeter of this hexagon,
we see that it is exactly zero since the individual pieces in the circles cancel out.
And that's exactly the perimeter of the triangle in the middle
by the theorem we just proved.
So the main diagonals of the hexagon meet at one point.
Now we only have to perform the transformation from the Poincaré model to the Klein model.
The statement also applies here because the intersection points of the diagonals
continue to run through a point.
This corresponds exactly to the scenario from the original Seven Circles Theorem,
which we have thus proved.